So Italy will be coming out onto court first and well no surprise is really with the starting line up that
Giamma Renzo Blengini has gone with.
Wantarena number five is going through the outside.
Simone Gneli number six just 20 years of age is the starting setter.
If Anzai 7 number nine the Zah is going through the opposite slot.
Philippa Lanza number 10 is through the outside.
Simone Bouti number 11 starts through the middle and the captain.
Imann Wellie Birerale number 15 is the other middle blocker.
Massimo Kalachi number 13 is the Libero defensive specialist.
That's the starting seven.
Gianna Lorenzo Blengini having faith in this team.
This is the team that beat Brazil 3-1.
Matteo Piano started in the first set in that match but was replaced by Birerale who didn't then come off.
And as we expected a big roar as Brazil get ready to come out onto court.
Starting with the captain.
Resende known as Bruno the setter.
It will be Wallace to Suza number four through the opposite slot.
Philippa Fontele s number 12 gets his start through the outside.
It's been a really good story for him and this Olympic Games having been on the bench for most of it.
Got his opportunity and has taken it.
It's Suza number 13 through the middle.
Look a sat count number 16 the other middle hitter and Ricardo.
Lookarali number 18 the outside hitter the Libero Sergio number 10.
40 years of age brought back from retirement.
This is last Olympic Games come what made very unlikely to see him in four years time.
So a few bits of a tremolo and just need to be let loose really a few blocks being done and want players now.
Just want to get this ready.
But the second referee is checking the rotations making sure that everyone's where they need to be so that Libero can come in.
And as soon as that's done we'll be ready to get this one underway.
It's the two time finalists against the two time champions.
It's 2004 revisited Brazil versus Italy for the goal medal.
Brazil triumph that day.
Italy though have overcome every challenge thrown their way in Rio 2016.
They beat Brazil 3100 pool match here eight days ago.
But this is the final.
China's women had been beaten by Serbia in their pool match and they came back to win the goal medal.
Italy have never won gold Brazil in their fourth consecutive final are going for their third title.
Italy in blue Brazil in yellow and Italy will start this final Simone Bouti.
First point to Italy off Wallace.
Just slightly put out a position Wallace trying to get that ball back into play.
So a good start for Italy having a point from the serving line.
Be it a relief we'll go once again.
So I said Lanza and Bouti waiting in the front row to try and stop whatever Brazil have to offer.
Look at early has to measure that.
Just as well there was a breakdown.
There were two touch there on the side of Brazil but that was a breakdown surely in the way that Italy were approaching that from a back court pipe.
I think there was a little bit of perspiration on the ball as Gianneli went to set that double touch call against him as it slipped through his fingers.
But the passing unit for Brazil is yet to get any confidence at the moment.
Two terrible passes that have put them under pressure.
A little bit of luck gets them out of it.
Look at early can be a demon server.
As his right thigh bound injured himself from the quarter final against Argentina was a doubt when he comes off what's this.
When he doesn't ignore that.
Just a little bit of nerves at this early stage because this is so much expectation riding on this team.
The women lost in the quarter finals.
Brazil ranked number one in their fourth final in a row.
And this is a man they need to keep very quiet.
Ivan Zitecev.
Take that.
Lovely blocking from Italy.
They slowed the ball down on that quick attack from Brazil.
Got it into transition and they were able to come back on the back court pipe of their own.
A skill or play that's widely is regarded as something that Brazil invented.
Everyone's copied.
And now certainly everyone else as good as Brazil and if some instances better.
Now the great serve dug well by look at early.
Confidence start badly so far.
His Zitecev once more.
And then off the block.
It's out and it's four one didn't land inside the court.
This man can pack a punch with a serve.
He ended one of the sets in the semi-files with three successive bases and he holds it.
And then he's going to have to go back to the goal.
This man can pack a punch with a serve.
He ended one of the sets in the semi-files with three successive bases and he holds the Olympic record.
127 kilometers an hour.
It's getting that balance right between power speed and accuracy.
What's interesting about Zitecev at the moment, even as though as that one goes wide,
is the fact that there's no celebration about what he's done so far.
He's constantly focused on getting this job done and doing the business.
No over celebrations, no show of emotion at the moment.
Bronze medalists in 2012 were Italy.
And it's your Dessousa, middle blocker.
The Le Po'lanta goes long and very, very high.
Whether he was going to try and get touch off the fingers.
And he was looking for block out and then trying to claim it.
And then that's just just looking at Bernardiniot to say the lads have come on.
What are you playing at? Why are you even trying to suggest we touched it?
Brazil just one point in a reels.
Starting slowly but steadily.
On off the block, Zitecev, there's a bit of a roar.
You'll see plenty of those.
If this develops like the bronze medal match earlier, went to five sets.
The USA were two sets to love down, but they came back in five sets.
There is a great value set on momentum in volleyball, but you've got to keep it going.
Because if it one drops, you could be in trouble.
Well, it's the loss. The set for 25 to 9.
Glencini decided, I've got a rest all my starting six.
Did that and they come back with a bang to take the match.
And now this is an even bigger test for them.
Despite the fact they've beaten Brazil already.
OK, there's a bit of bragging rights, but in the context of this, it really doesn't mean anything at all.
Here's the top point scorer in the Olympic Games.
127 to his name. Wallace.
That's too long. One of the top servers as well.
That wasn't quite there. All players just finding their range.
Key to get the ball over the net in these early stages.
Don't get left behind.
Italy had France eight love down in the first set in their first match.
Middle blocker, Lucas.
It's the Modena connection.
Bruno and Lucas play together in Italy against these guys on a regular basis.
They're on the same rotation for their club as they are for their national team.
And they know each other inside out where that ball needs to go and where you'll see as well.
Lucas will run maybe an A quick then come back behind if the ball's out of position.
And Bruno will find him. Good leave that.
Although it's been given as an A serve by the first referee, Leapay has come up with the ace.
He gets 10 out of 10 for coolness. How about that?
Three your legs. That's out.
And then suddenly the line just says no it's not.
And here's the first challenge.
Just as in tennis, this is like the Hawkeye.
Has that ball landed out? Is it on the line?
Any part of the ball catches any part of that line.
It's in five challenges.
But you could have five elements to the challenge system.
Ball in X.
And it is indeed in some Leapay has his ace.
Block touch, neck touch and ten attention then football.
Center line, three meter line or service line.
We are all square.
Intense concentration.
Great dig by Colachi.
And then Wantarena across court.
The nephew of the great Alberto Wantarena, the Cuban runner.
Double gold medalist in Montreal.
You can see the family likeness and you can see the height as well.
And the power of the man as well.
Where are the top strikers of the ball for Italy?
And they're back in front.
Great blocking from Italy.
And all off the back of some good serving from Giannelli.
This is a strong rotation for the Italians.
They've got Zite's in the front row.
And they've got Beer are really those two combining well to shut down Luca.
Now this is a good position at the moment for Italy to be in.
Building points, building a lead.
Giannelli, 20 last Thursday.
And the rising stars of the games.
Good serve.
Brilliant by Colachi.
Oh, another finish by Wantarena.
96.
Italy definitely mean business here.
Really good pick up by the Libero full stretch.
And then Zite's aim acting as setter.
To give Wantarena the opportunity to go past Lucas.
Bruno not deciding to block he wishes he had now.
These Liberos are outstanding athletes.
The grace, the strength, they're the smallest on the court.
But they have to do so much.
They're going to be in the front.
Giannelli.
Have to stay in the back court.
They can't serve and they can't spike.
But there is an element of going to the front court.
But they have to stay low below the net.
You will see Sergio jumping from behind the three meter line to set the ball up for an attack.
He can then set it inside the three.
So will Colachi.
But they're setting that lead to attack the ball.
And if they were to set that ball, that's a really good dig.
And it was attacked.
And it would be an illegal play.
What a play though from Italy.
Soaking up the pressure of the Brazilian attack.
Brilliant setting from Zite's end.
Who's fan Wantarena again?
What a combination.
Those two are providing to him for each other.
No, it's pos one you want arena to serve.
Good, Dipper.
Sergio keeps it up.
And then Leepay off the block.
Off the fingertips, lands out of the court.
He's ill point.
You have to give Leepay the ultimate credit.
Nice pick up from Sergio.
But Leepay was in the 2012 squad for the London Games.
Went to the test event but was then cut from the team that actually ended up going.
Mistangue of the Olympics.
And there's now come back into the squad again and forced his way into the starting six.
Finds himself an Olympic final four years later.
What a swipe down the line there by it.
Emmanuel Libertad-Eli, the captain.
In his second Olympic Games, 35 years old.
This could be his swan song.
And that was a mighty hit by passing the block, deading it in the corner.
Keeps Brazil playing catch up.
And here is the captain.
Well left.
It's his trademark serve.
Beerelli is serves from jump float serve from five to five.
But he is the same.
And it's that mix up of jump float serves and jump serves.
That always keeps the serving unit, the service unit on their toes.
Players move round in rotation.
4-3-2 at the front of the net.
1-6-5.
That's going from right to left in the move and in a clockwise position.
Lanza unable to keep that back in play.
And look at Eli just starts to show why he's so highly rated.
One of the youngest players on the roster.
Lanza not moving his feet properly unable to contain the ball.
His arms outside his body line.
That was why he was beaten.
Because there is average age 30, Italy 28.
Here is the new generation.
Youngest.
Douglas who is on the bench.
That's one of the replacements in this roster.
Here is Zyte, sheaping up.
And gets that off the block.
Off the touch.
12-10.
Brazil will feel that Lanza is probably the weak point in the Azuris attack
and defense and they will look to pin and go after him.
Likewise, Italy will probably look to go after Lepe.
And they will feel they have better matchups through the middle.
They will need to get their serves in to maintain that pressure.
There's an unexpected calm about side 7, the Italians.
Minimum effort for a bigger return at the moment.
Because there may well be bigger battles to come.
If we're set for five sets that could be two and a half hours play.
Stacey Plier is a great dig from Bruno.
Usually didn't get a hold of that one.
Zyte has does.
Again, a great pick up by Bruno.
And then off the touch.
That's good.
And there's the Raw.
They're running on emotion here.
That can be positive.
It can also be negative.
Let's see.
Women found.
They're running on emotion here.
That can be positive.
It can also be negative.
Let's see.
Women found.
When the crowd couldn't lift them and they're gained disintegrated.
But here, Brazill's men have exactly the result they wanted and their level.
They've run this for Suza.
Great block by Italy, but it's it's dropped out of the court.
Gienelli was there.
Lovely fast ball from Bruno.
He's gone.
He's on the pin at two and he said that ball all the way over to the other side.
Really quickly.
No chance for Italy to get their blocks.
He's got a good ball.
Saints for Italy to get their blocks set properly and Le quais gets the wall
off of the hands and out of play.
And just like that, that serving room from Suza as put Brazilian front.
fore the first time in the match.
Brazil also taking the chance to be spoken to by their coach, but Italy have chosen to go off the court.
They are going to be in the right direction.
So, before we move on to our second highly populated midfielder.
We are going to be in eight years of với-2.
O prochain cause we never park onto mind when we are saying that football.
the goal.
It was just one.
How will they counter this run by
Sousa who continues spinning some
magic from the back court.
The answer is he continues was that
in.
It was just out.
The block was there but it just
dropped outside the court.
Relief for Zaitsev.
It's been a while since he was
in the back court.
Another challenge for Brazil as
well is it's been a dinner just
keeping his calm during the course
of this because he is such a
colorful character.
He needs to make sure that he's
in control seeing what's happening
as his challenge is going to be
looked at and reviewed and it has
landed in.
It's a big point for Brazil.
Zaitsev is stuffed.
Lippe lining up Lucas.
Downing Zaitsev.
That is significant.
Zaitsev is one of the big hitters
the big strikers.
Keep him quiet.
And Italy could be struggling.
And Brazil have just gone two points
clear and he's still on serve.
And that is a delapse of
concentration on one hand but
also difficult to proceed that
that swirled as it came.
This is why teams will mix up
between the jump floats and the
jumpsuit but look at this.
This is such a run from Suza.
Three aces already now.
But what Italy do have to do is
present a different picture.
They're lining up the same way and
they're not being able to deal
with it.
Present a different picture.
Stand a bit further back.
Move a bit wider.
Give Suza something to think about.
Lippe goes cross court and he's
found the ground.
16-12.
What a shift.
Brilliant pick up from Bruno.
Show us the desire.
And then this is all out from Lippe.
This man means business.
He was struggling with injury.
An initial part of Rio 2016 and
it's time out too.
Italy worried.
It's too far away.
If the ball is slow,
if the ball is less,
the other thing on this ball is
difficult to enter the ball.
You can try to make a step in the
direction.
Come on.
Italy behind in a match.
Only once so far in Rio 2016
when they feel that a weakened
team in their final poolay in
counter against Canada when they
went down three-one, lost the
first set, 25-23.
What a run for this man.
Mr. Carm.
the
first time in the
game.
Break through for
Booty.
It's going to be very
important that Italy can run
there middle and create gaps
for site.
For when to rain are on the
pipe and Lanza right wide.
Good work from Booty.
Lanza.
Good for Wallace.
Watch his back.
They're not the easiest.
Good block by Brazil.
And today that.
Off the touch and off the block.
It's out 14 16.
Ploy their way back.
Good high hands hit taking on
Wallace.
Vanta rain that.
Getting high hard and into that
far corner.
The greatest distance you have
to hit through that position
through for is to the opposite
corner.
But this is an issue.
Italy going from the serving
line and it is obviously a high
risk serve.
But at this level.
It's expected to get it in.
However, in this match, the
pressure is definitely on both
sides regardless.
That's that balance between
keeping it in play and try to rock
your rivals.
Which is what this man normally
does.
It's a good one.
Brilliant ace.
Didn't pull out all the burners.
But it did enough.
But it's good disguise from Wallace.
Looks like it's going to hit hard.
Just rolls it over the screen.
And Lanza not being able to read it.
No one thing that blend.
Genie was talking about in the
timeout was saying to the lads.
Look, we need a better ball in.
To Gneli here because things
aren't working.
And as a result, Lanza has gone
off.
And he's going to be able to
play the ball.
And he's going to be able to see
these in to do some passing.
It's normally a libero.
But he's being used here as a
passer-hitter.
But primarily just a passer
defender.
Wallace now with the serve again.
If in doubt, blasts.
I'm Thorena tries it.
But Brazilla still on it.
And off the touch.
They've got another point.
1914.
Well, Italy will not be
particularly happy about that.
That said, it's going to be
a bit more than a second.
But I think it's going to be
And then it's going to be a bit
happy about that.
That set from Sergio wasn't the
best.
As he looked like a double touch.
But the player was allowed to
continue and then Wallace gets
it off the hands of booty.
Gets it off the block and away.
We can see why the fingers are
all strapped up.
Because this man has with a lot
of the players on his side of the
net can't absolutely hammer it
across.
It's a double edge sword really at
this level of getting your
fingers wrapped from the ball
and also with the amount of
times you're hitting that ball.
It does break the skin.
So a lot of the players took
these lights and strapping up
his fingers.
So he doesn't end up with very
sore hands.
He's trying to make sore hands
of look early and he's done it
on that occasion.
Managed to get through the
block and then off the touch
off the net or off the court.
It's 1915.
They pulled another point back.
First to 25 and it's the best
of five sets.
Still to get the impression
of it about third gear.
And now Oleg Antonov
naturalised Russian playing
for Italy.
Serving specialist.
This needs to be good in the
Olympic final.
And it is.
That's come straight back
over almost.
And then the block from
Binnenelli.
Following up.
That is an amazing piece of
hang time for Binnenelli
because he was in the
first touch, the second touch
coming over and he's jumped
with the setter.
Realised it's going to the
middle but then thought I can
stay here.
And he did.
And he makes the block.
That was something special.
Brazil need to take the time out.
Just stop this recovery in its
tracks.
And then the other one
is the second touch.
And he's jumped with the setter.
Realised it's going to the middle
but then thought I can stay here.
And he did.
And he makes the block.
That was something special.
Unfortunately, the middle one was
going for it.
Here we go!
It was a good score.
I am the second 3 points
in the T1 matchup next weekend or
first Friday.
Then everyone's here.
Thank you for the time.
Italy have never won
the last time in the final, 2004 Athens against this team, Brazil and they lost.
Eight days ago they beat them in the pool match, he's 3-1, the same score line.
Wallace didn't get that right.
Arrived like a train, but then through the buffers at the other side of the court.
Just down to 2 now.
This is what's so good about Italy and the way that they've performed throughout this Olympic Games.
They have not been phased by the fact that they have found themselves behind and they just come back at you and come back at you.
Where they came up from, that 25th thrashing in set 4 is extraordinary against the United States.
This is quite reasonable at the moment.
They're adrenaline charge and surge there through the serving arm of Antonov.
And so Brazil first to 20 and 3 points clear.
Important now though that Italy managed their side out, don't allow any points from Brazil.
Double substitution called by Brazil and that puts if Andrew into the front row replacing Bruno.
And William has come into replace Wallace in the back row, set as in the back row now.
And that'll be for another 9 rotations, 3 huge front court attackers as Leopold gets ready with the jump serve.
Quite big there, magnificent by Rossini. You can tell he's a liberal.
Net touch given against Brazil as they went after that one.
And that's a really good dig for William's just walked on to court and he's dug an absolute thumper from side-cept.
Only to find one of his teammates has touched them now.
That's why the second of the fish is there.
So Gianelli.
Oh yes, look at Ali Wate, Leopold.
It's a leap and it's the speed of the attack.
This ball out wide that is coming from Bruno.
And equally from Gianelli is not giving any chance at all for the middle blockers on the other side to get up and join up with the outside blocker.
So we're going to see a lot of open space cross court on both sides.
Lucas middle blocker goes long.
Little Luke stay just about in touch 1921.
But it's no good just winning one point now. They need two or three to take the fight in this first set to Brazil.
Lancer back into the front row. I see him's done his job.
Passing and defending now. I'm today in the opposite.
I wouldn't have smoothed it might have been.
If we had the chance now. Here's Lancer back off.
But what a block. Evandro, that's why he's on.
He is a giant.
Absolutely enormous.
And just reaches up hanging there.
Well, it's the speed of the ball out wide but it was just dying inside.
And that just played right into Susa and Evandro's hands literally into Susa's hands.
And if Andrew, well, they enjoy that.
So the double substitutions now have been reversed. Bruno's back in.
He's going to go and serve.
And that means Wallace is into the front row.
And Andrew, very much having done his job successfully.
That's the best way to respond. He's just been blocked as Lancer.
And then Jean-Ele says, no, I trust you. He go.
Have another go. I'll reestablish you.
He's dead and he's now a threat again.
Pass the block. Italy.
Just moving through the gears now.
Because this is important.
If they can take this first set, silence the home crowd.
What a comeback.
And then he attacked it. Set it to Wallace.
Lancer goes for the tip.
Here he comes again, Wallace.
Oh, yes. He's failed to get it.
It's out.
He looked as if it was absolutely nailed.
But he pushed it wide.
Now, Wallace's technique through the left hand side of court
doesn't suit his body type.
He's a player that, with the way that he comes in,
is always rotating to his left.
And he was very tight on the left hand side.
He's over-rotated.
And that's why he's missed the sideline.
This is not work. They should have done before.
This is perspiration from the players. It has to be cleared.
Any moisture on that court surface can be critical
in terms of causing slips, damaged ankles.
It has to be absolutely dry.
Be an early now.
This is much more like it for Italy.
A little bit of emotion from Susa.
Lansian, hurried and unruffled.
As good as Wallace is, as good as Cite's,
as good as Luke Carelli, Leapay, Lanza,
and Wantaraina is this game is probably going to be one
and lost on both teams' ability to get their middles running.
Get that quick ball in and put it on the floor.
From the opposed to Luke Carelli,
to give Brazil set point.
And he's done it.
What a belter.
And what a time to do it.
Just as Italy were coming back,
take that three set points to the hosts.
And as well as being able to get their middles running,
it's vitally important that the serving brings that kind of heat and pressure
because that could be the difference.
It's certainly the difference in this set,
Brazil's serving runs now topped off by that ace from Luke Carelli
as putting them in the driving seat.
Listen to the crowd there, expectant.
One point save, Cite's ev.
And this is a man who is more than capable of turning this around
and giving Italy the set.
The way he blasted through the USA in the semifinal
three aces to round off a Rousing 5 set up.
That's not the way he wanted to win that first set
and Brazil have taken it 25-22.
They came from behind
and they've closed out Italy.
Advantage, the host nation.
25-22, just as.
It was pretty close in the first set in their pool match
when they won 25-23.
But Brazil came bounding back and took the next,
or Italy came bounding back and took the next three sets.
Brazil will resume.
One set to the good and Luke Carelli will pick up
by those famous five rings.
That's the way to start for Osmani Juantarina.
Under a little bit of pressure from the surf, however,
Ginelli gets the ball back out into position where he's able to put it away.
And at this level, that is as good as you can expect
in terms of swing hitting.
And he's going to be ready to go.
The youngest man on the court, 20 years old, Ginelli.
Great dig by Leapay.
What a stop to himself.
And Cite's there!
One fist pump.
That tells you he's just starting to rev up.
The engine's warming now.
Good use of the block.
Leapay then getting hit by Susa.
Ginelli just snatching at that one.
He had a nice good position.
Didn't hit right up onto the ball.
And that pike, as he went to make contact,
just forcing that ball into the net.
Such an experienced coach Bruno Razzendi.
This is his fourth finalist coach.
One the first one.
One is up in the last two.
But ahead.
On his home court.
They'll take that off the touch then.
Just inside the court.
Susa, couldn't get down quick enough.
Italy delighted to have got off that serve as well.
Last time in the first set, it costed my whole heap of points.
Although they still were under pressure from the serve.
They were in the middle of the net.
Once around, they got them out of trouble.
Just taking his time.
Oh, yes.
And to good effect.
It's so important you have a pre-serve routine.
Once you get going, that you are set.
You know exactly what you're going to do.
Bruno's just saying,
Bruno, I'm going to have a challenge here because the flag
on the line's official said out.
And also what I'm doing as well as I'm just slowing things
down again without taking a time out.
That means Wancering is going back to the serving line.
He's starting again.
You look at serving at this level and you talk about going in
runs of three.
That one quite clearly in.
Never in doubt as far as anyone was concerned.
But he would then look to have gone a little bit harder.
Perhaps with this next one until he was up to what he would consider
his full speed jumpsup.
Now he's starting again.
Calm, composed, and in play.
So that was cross-court.
Just a cup on a steps.
What is doesn't have a huge run-up that you see Zites have.
He just won two and then bang.
He pings up in the air.
He's like Tigger.
He gets so high and then absolutely cracks that ball over the block.
Tigger didn't like climbing trees, but he certainly does.
He can get up to a mighty height.
And here it comes again.
Still in play.
Has to go over now.
There's Wallace.
And look at that.
Off the block.
He's got a great chase from him.
And then Sergio puts it into a spot where Wallace can take on the block.
He goes high hands.
Doesn't try and bury it.
And they have the point.
And Jettis importantly, Wallace still has serve.
The noise from the crowd grows again.
They're one set to the good.
Just too long.
No challenge coming.
All going to Resende's way.
As his son Bruno the captain.
And his third Olympic game, Zites having his second.
Wallace in his second.
So much experience.
He's the turning captain.
Man, you really bit it, Ellie.
I'm going to get the ball.
You really bit it, Ellie.
That's the touch.
It's that lovely middle move.
Set, blocker.
Thank you.
It's the simplest and most effective play in volleyball.
Good ball in.
A quick attacker up in the air.
Almost before the ball is in the set as hands.
And then you're under pressure.
Lucas was up and over-booty before he could get anywhere near it.
That's the only way he could get there.
The only way he could get there.
Let's go.
Lepe.
Well left says Kalachi.
No challenge.
Why didn't he play still?
13 kilometres now.
Fastest so far.
And if you thought that serving was to start to rally then think again.
Serving is to win points.
And Zites going to try and do the same here for it.
That was a tough one.
And Lucas isn't just a middle blocker with a mighty swing.
That was a delicate tip.
And not only that.
Lepe under extreme pressure.
The ball was going behind Brenner.
He's had to readjust to go backwards.
And then they have the point.
You don't get two points for his and it hard.
I think he forgot that.
He always gives it a mighty welt.
No half measures with Lucas.
Doesn't necessarily provide the delicacy of touch to his serve.
Racies, aces rather are rare.
I think it's really tough.
He's a great swing.
He needs one now.
The lands up.
And off the block.
While this does the business just as Italy were threatening to have a little break.
Three points clear.
It's back to one.
and then even Lancer, which is why ended up tipping it over.
And that gave the Brazilian team the initiative then
to put it into transition.
Lancer then up for the back court pipe, as they call it.
Set it to a hitter who has to take off from the back court.
Can't be in the front.
Wallace, magnificent dig there by Zitesv.
Wallace again, three blockers across the net.
And he has to go wide or push it wider than them,
but it was just heading out of the court.
The angle was so tight.
It's just the dilemma you have as a hitter,
trying to avoid the block, but then you're running out of court space
as opposed to trying to go block out.
Which would have been off the Italian blockers finger tips
and landing out of the court and therefore point to Brazil.
So a bit of a momentum for Italy.
Oh, yes.
How neat was that?
That's what you call a positive set.
That ball in from Leipa going towards Bruno.
He helps it on his way behind him.
Extra little bit of speed on it.
Nice positive set. Pressure on Italy.
Could only get one blocker up and look
at Ellie with no trouble putting it down.
It's about isolating or overloading the block.
Can you find your way past these three giants
who are normally bounding from side to side in the court?
They look big and they are, but they can move fast too.
A rare era by look at Ellie.
That could be an devilish serve to get over.
That had just caught the top of the net
and died the other side with all the saying what a serve.
It's something that the world governing body
are looking at actually post-disci Olympic games.
The ball that hits the net and dribbles over
would be given as a let.
Like a tennis and we get to serve again.
Leipaid. Digs and then spikes.
Wonderful by Brazil.
Well that free ball over and suddenly you've got Suza
and Wallace both behind Bruno coming in on a combination
play a C2 and looking at the up goes Wallace.
Bear are really had to commit with Suza
and there's just enough space to get in.
So we can commit with Suza and there's just enough space
for him to put the ball away.
Just to point in it.
Suza.
Just another game for him isn't it?
That's the way he's approaching it.
So calm.
Oh yes, Lucas.
And one is together and those two points
have been gobbled up and Brazil a back level.
What a block.
Monster block ringing out around the Marrakemen's
Zinho and it was exactly that.
It's really can't break away Brazil just keep pulling them back.
And it's Suza again spinning his web.
That is an insane set from Giannelli.
One handed and he doesn't go in front.
He sets it behind him.
And gets a one or one as a result.
That is incredible.
Just 20 years of age and in a maturity of a 30 year old.
He's the best setter as well in the competition.
Outstanding.
Watching two just tip them all over and take the point as well.
Not always setting.
Just getting carried away.
And what was a 10-line lead is now 10 all.
One thing we haven't seen much from Italy at the moment.
It's just drifted away a bit and something that blend gene has been asking his team to do in this second set.
It's to start getting that pike running.
They need to be a little bit more active in that area to try and put more pressure on Brazil.
Bringing the back court players in, setting it so that the big hitters in the back court
arrive flying through the air.
Check if you roll this.
You know, there he goes quickly.
And that's often a familiar tactic on both sides of the net.
The setter short and fast to his middle blocking companion and bang down it goes.
What was special about that was the fact that there wasn't much room for beer to work with.
He had to actually turn that across his body in order to get it into court.
Because the angle otherwise would have seen him go and hit somebody on the bench.
Like chess at the moment, physical chess.
One point and then strategy as to the players move around.
Can they find a way through?
And then there's the physical part blasted by Lepe.
There is so much technical, tactical information going on.
Each and every time the ball is served, Lepe with a brilliant swing cross court,
brute power from him.
Lepe now to serve his rotation.
One through inner hit the back court pipe.
Saved by Sergio.
And then, when he kept in there by one through inner, that was out surely.
That's close to the net. It's going to be difficult for it.
They're going to have come again.
And that's out. And there was no touch.
What a dig from Sergio.
40 years of age.
Age really means nothing.
He's already assured of his fourth Olympic medal.
Gold silver silver.
And you know what he's going to get in 2016.
That will put him on a par with Tetsukin of Russia and San Juan Papi of Italy as well.
Those two with four Olympic medals.
One of the great to the sport.
Retired after 2012.
But then brought back last year.
That will be Brazil's goal because Gianelli has taken that from the side of Brazil.
Just like the saw in the first set, Brazil.
So king up the pressure for Italy and now they have the lead when Gini calls the timeout.
We have the goal, the patience, the win, the win, the win, the win.
Think about it when we have the right to win.
We have to look for the win, the win, the win.
We have to win, the win.
And not everything is going to be the first.
The second with the goal, we have to use the win.
We have to give it to our best.
They have never been two sets down at Rio 2016.
They are still in touch but they know that if Brazil carry on like this just as they did in the first set.
Just keep them at an arm's length.
They take that second set.
It will be a huge challenge to come back.
And Brazil know equally that getting two sets up in an Olympic final really doesn't mean a great deal.
They know all of that from London 2012 when they were two up against Russia and they had swings from match point.
Only to lose it 26-24 and then lose the next two and end up with a silver.
112 kilometres an hour. Take that for an ace.
There is going to be a challenge. It was called as out but you just got to love Lepe.
And all he has been through, his back story is incredible in terms of why you see how he has got here.
Not only getting here but being on the bench at the start of this tournament and now he is very much an influential fligger in what Brazil are doing.
In Genie Convinced that was absolutely out but we are about to fight out from Hawkeye.
Italy requesting this challenge.
How many Italian fingers are crossed?
It's in.
Italy haven't just lost the point. They have also lost a challenge.
They have one left in this set.
That's a bit of a hand-doll expression from Ivan Zitev and more for the coach to Ponder.
Three points in it now.
I am going to tell the team that they need to be in this for the long game.
Don't rush things. Go for block outs. Get themselves back in this one point at a time.
There is a point.
Off the block from Zitev, power and it ricocheted off that Brazilian block.
The arm is outstretched. Out of court, back court.
The danger is that big power on the arm is really over.
Hang in it, drop, track down on the other side of the net and lose the point.
They are dead by loophole.
Three touches either side.
Good decision by Zitev.
For those of you that may have watched cricket and understand what that's like and maybe have been face to few fast bowlers in your life.
This is exactly what it's like stood there in the receive unit when you've got Zitev coming out here.
You've got Wanta and Cine.
Look and see Leapay's eyes the way he's trying to take in as much information as possible from the contact of the arm movement to contact.
Then it's fractions of a second before it's on to you.
Now roll reverse.
It's like screaming as well by the Italian players.
There's Giannelli trying one of his specials but Brazil reading that.
Both teams out of system at the moment.
What it says a chance.
But he's too big.
Leapay saying no.
But Nadine was going to challenge.
Lovely dig from Zitev in that rally.
But as a result of that he was completely out of it.
And that meant there was only the pipe or potentially a ball at four.
Again, didn't quite work.
Both teams still had a system.
It might want to call boot even he's got so much tape on his hands.
It's difficult for us to see with the broadcast picture if it caught him.
However, the challenge system.
Cameras which have hundreds of frames per second will have spotted that if there was one without any question at all.
It's unequivocal evidence.
And it didn't touch anybody.
If you'll get the point, the challenge system introduced to volleyball after London 2012 in the club World Championship.
The goal is to get the ball back.
A hesitation.
A motion.
It's a roar of relief.
He's done a fabulous job.
Up to game speed.
Straight away.
Gegen the block out.
They're answer is who's gone to the bench.
Here is Antonov.
28 years old.
Just breaking into the Italian team.
the game against Canada but by the end of the match after about three sets he'd really
found his rhythm but Italy need to find his rhythm right now. If they lose this second
set, problems, Bruno now, the Brazilian captain.
Fanta Reyna, more like it.
Well, for those of you watching this on television, that's an instance where you can add
actually feel the physicality of that swing. How he has put everything into that.
Almost bursting the ball. That's how much it means to him. He's desperate to get his
team up and running here.
Generate this momentum. It's been elusive to the team in blue.
Suza, my turn, I'll whack it and do 17-16 from the middle.
This has been struggling with a slight back issue during the course of this Olympics.
And Edair was actually starting ahead of him.
He's been able to get himself back fully fit and that's a huge bonus for Brazil.
This could be Wallace finishing it. Great block by the Italian captain.
Absolutely determined there. As Wallace attempted to go cross court, Biddo Reilly was waiting right arm.
Shut down that cross court angle very nicely. Wallace thought he had it and then he had to think again.
That's what you call a negative set. We've seen the positive set where the ball comes into the set
and he continues it on its way. That's a negative set. It's come into Bruno.
He's had to hold it, send it back out the way it's come. But he's done it really well because not without
it would be a slower ball. But he's put great speed on that to still give leap at the chance to go block out.
Not the best dig there by Zite. That's close to the net as well.
They get the point but that was more by good luck than good management.
Once you get there they do say the more you play the luckier you get there.
He's been playing for a long time but he knew in that situation what he had was just I've got to go block out.
And he's done it brilliantly. Interestingly that Zite said was in the passing unit.
They keep Zite said out and complete these. The opposite player big hitter.
Not the best of passes. However, saying that again he has played as an outside hitter.
And Blengini was gambling with him as an outside hitter at the start of the World League finals but didn't go very well.
He's playing like a man possesses an elite pay. Serving, hitting, receiving and above all scoring.
Great technique from the elite pay. Getting that ball over his shoulder.
Not much room to work with and still getting the block out.
He gives that everything he's got every time he touches the ball.
Back across.
Hands reaching, Antonov. He's in all his height then. And now Zite said.
Just off the touch, off the block, 19 all. They're sticking with Brazil.
But the moment they can't get ahead of them.
They are wearing them down. That's the thing. We haven't seen Lucas have a swing for a while.
We haven't seen Suza have a swing for a while. So that means that it's in his serving pressure has gone up.
It's relying on Leopie and Wallace at the moment to get the job done.
Another good one for Wise.
Well, you have to be careful.
And quite rightly, the first referee just said calm down and trace Ennevich.
It's a very experienced referee just saying that's enough calm down.
But that tells you, Wallace is getting a little bit frustrated here with the way that the fact that actually they're not getting away from Italy.
He's just got that ball down in front of Antonov who couldn't close his block and he vented that frustration on the ball.
Like leading the football match one-0, having the chances and not being able to take them.
Italy, as in football, doggardly defending.
Staying in touch, keeping in the game.
Here's Zyteceb.
Get to the point.
And a long time this goes on.
There's still in there. We've seen it in the past.
In the last few matches in the semifinals.
The team which has dominated, suddenly finds itself level with the team they were overwhelming at one stage or at least leading.
And then they go and concede match per set point and they lose it having squandered three or four of their own.
Italy trying to come late and surprise Brazil.
It's in it's in it's an ace.
The crowd baby, Westing, try to put him off.
But Zyteceb has had the last laugh.
The crowd baby Westing trying to put him off.
He's going a bit worried for the team.
He's going a bit worried because it's in the lead.
The crowd baby Westing trying to put him off.
We're going to the first round.
I've no worry inside to see a player like that receiving treatment,
but we've seen ice packs placed on people's neck shoulders,
but they still go out and swing and flash the ball at more than 100 kilometers now
when it comes to serving and also spiking.
So, Lukarelli did land awkwardly in the quarterfinal against Argentina
and needed treatment.
But he is back on court.
Italy have the serve though.
Even to get to 25 to level at one set all.
And here is Zytev once more.
Zytev unload again.
They claim there was a touch.
Brazil say that was out.
And there's the buzzer saying,
challenge by Italy.
Well, that's the brilliance of this system because to the human eye
the ball did go out.
It went miles out and we didn't see it.
What? Tell you what, it's close.
The frames per second don't do that just as we can't quite see.
That may have clipped.
That may have touched that middle finger.
They're watching.
And they're celebrating.
Well, they're not celebrating now because it's been given against
the problem.
As we see on that from the broadcast camera,
the ball is a shadow of the ball.
Now, as you see the shadow of the ball come over.
Yeah, it couldn't have like it's touched it.
But I couldn't see any movement of the finger.
And the cameras that are being used to monitor that are very different to the ones that are being shown
here in the hall.
We can tell what Italy think of it.
They thought they had that.
Well, Blengini goes and looks at this after.
Should he need to go and look at it?
You'll be proven that that ball didn't touch the block.
Double substitution then.
Vibrasil, what we've seen in set one.
Evandro and William R. In Bruno and Wallace are out.
Blengini is still fuming.
He can rage at the officials all he likes but the point is it's 21 all.
And it's only to get on with this match.
Zite's head will take it off the block.
If they're not going to get that serve or the challenge right, then they can at least score.
Well, this is where you just have to let the volleyball do the talking.
That's what Zite's head does is he gets that off of Lucarelli.
And away.
No question he touched that one.
Trying to go down the line.
Good effort.
He's just taking on that line.
He's taking on the extra.
The hand near is the antenna.
The touch is the antenna as well.
That's certainly point to the opposition.
So Antonov.
Getting into a bit of rhythm now.
Still in play.
But it was over the court.
They needed to drop fast and it's not.
It's out of court now.
22 all.
Superb setting from Bruno.
Taking that ball and sending it all the way out to Wallace.
And that said.
Italy's block scrambling to the left.
Try and get towards him.
Now to double figures.
Wallace 10 for the match.
137 over all.
What a valuable player.
And this could be problems for Italy.
And they've taken the point.
23 22.
And they're closing in on this second set for a two set lead.
Gnelly's gone after that.
When he shouldn't just waited.
He could have played that back off of it.
That was an amazing pick up by Zite.
Which hasn't been converted.
Brazil.
Will be serving.
Will be serving for set point.
But it's time out for Italy.
So you start.
Yes.
It's a game that I know.
I have to say it's a game.
Oh.
Hey.
You're doing it.
Yeah.
The court.
That's not.
OK.
In the end.
Hey.
The competition.
They know what they need to do.
It's just a question now.
I'm actually doing it.
Can they force Brazil?
They need the blinkers on right now.
Brazil not looking at the scoreboard.
Not looking to the referee.
Just focusing in on these next two points.
Or however many they might need to see them over the line.
And just get that little bit of breathing room.
And go to sets to nothing up.
And then they're going to be in.
And to not stand here's job.
Lans are now.
They need to continue on.
And hopefully get Italy back into this one.
Bruno the captain.
Can close this out.
Guantanana.
It's out.
No touch.
Set point.
Italy thought they had that.
Guantanana did.
Or wasn't necessarily the conviction.
And so it's proved.
And the referee just holds his arm out towards the team,
which has taken the point.
And with no challenges remaining,
Brazil have two set points.
Just gone long.
Tension moves up again.
23, 24.
Serve has to be good for Italy.
They have to make Brazil play.
Can they level at 24 all?
And if they can, just like in tennis,
the winner will be the team
which gets two points clear.
And Jenny was saying to his guys,
they know this game.
They know it's close.
He just needs them to step up.
Just play their game.
He believes in them.
He wants them to deliver.
The ball still in play.
This has to go over.
Three touches.
Leapay intervenes.
And it's level at 24 all.
That was just incredible from Gianneli.
He's completely out of position.
He's got his back to the net.
He jumps and spins and volleys it in.
And completely catches Brazil by surprise.
And now it's anyone's two points clear
is required to win this set.
Time out.
Resend needs a breather.
Look at that shaking ahead.
They've let it slip at the moment.
Wait, did you know?
Back you can't pick up.
Turn it in.
They'll pass you.
They're going to pass you.
They're going to throw in the first one.
Turn it in.
Captain in Manuel Bitter-Eli,
the
older smile on their side of the
net 35 years old issues that
rallying call their back on
court they have served.
Now can they capitalize.
Big blast from Wallace blocked.
Now look at Ellie the block has
landed and Italy have the point.
They have set point.
He is free.
Because they have the chance to
get the ball.
They have the point.
They have let it go.
Now as we said for Italy need
to make sure Brazil played.
They have got to get this over
and they have got to make sure
they are absolutely on it to
close out this set and level
one all.
Big blast.
Giazzi.
Giannelli.
And the block is there again.
And off the touch.
It's leveled at 25 all.
That was cool and calm under
the ball.
Because that ball could have
so easily have missed the block
and gone wide.
And we are all square again.
Great work by Sotinne coming in
with that serving run super pickup
as well to put Italy into that
set point opportunity.
But it's still Italy with the
advantage.
As long as they side out they're
side out for set point each
time.
Such pressure just to come on and
deliver.
Absolutely then.
Here's look at Ellie.
Oh costly.
What a time for
unforced error.
Another set point for Italy.
This is where Italy have the
ability to really go through
caution to the win from the
serve.
Because the other team are
expected to side out anyway.
Giannelli.
Oh, another enforced error.
But again, psychologically that's
not a problem.
We expect the other team to side
out.
So.
Go up.
Go for it.
If you can win it from the serve
brilliant because they can't
respond.
It's any side out game.
They're happy with that.
He's got three front court
options now.
When Serena and Bitter-Ele and
Zaitsev to choose from.
Suza with a serve.
But he has caused problems.
And then Gini might disagree
with you.
Let's see.
Now they finish it now.
And then he's going to be
a little bit more.
Yeah.
So.
Please give it a try.
So, it's not a problem.
Is that the first option?
Right.
I think that's he.
Can they finish it now?
Zaitsev?
Oh ho!
Mr Coul!
Off the block.
Zaitsev goes for it.
And Brazil.
Have set point for the first
time in this third set.
Well, what a turnaround.
Are you sure they won't
turn.
Well, they weren't when they
set the ball to Zaitsev.
They might be now.
But now a little bit of
very much now back in charge of the set.
Susa, he's done it again and they've taken it.
That mystery swarming serve decieves Lanza.
And from the set point that Italy had, Brazil have scored and they've taken
a two sets to love lead. How decisive will that be?
Because remember, in 2012, four years ago, they led two sets to love and they lost
three, two beaten by Russia.
Confirmation of the scores.
Very close second set. Italy had their chance, but it's Brazil who now lead to nothing.
Booty resumes for Italy.
Ah, brilliant.
He's been immense.
Straight away, Brazil established their middle attack.
Doesn't matter. It was a tip. The fact is the balls come in and Bruno has gone straight to Susa.
And straight away, he's a threat again. That's something for Italy to think about.
Such a deceptive presence.
Just moves around the court quite slowly,
unconcerned, rarely gets revved, but boys, he playing well.
That's a lead from look at Italy.
He's quite got his serving radar right.
But when you two set the good, all the pressures on that side on it,
there's Zite's ev. He needs some real magic.
As does this man, Gianelli.
That's me supporting Italy. A desperate for them to take this set for Brazil.
You want it done in three, particularly for the Brazilian fans, because they don't want to repeat
the four years ago. However, if Italy do take it, it's going to be fascinated to see
Brazil then respond. So much at stake. So much on the line.
There you go, Susa.
Having like two touches, but we'll play on.
He's got to move himself now, and he just can't quite get there.
Well, with the ability to be able to
highhand volley the first serve, it's certainly ever going to be an issue if the ball is caught.
You can get done for a carry off of the first serve, but you won't get caught for a double touch.
Good effort from Susa throwing himself at it.
Lucky the hoardings aren't made of stronger stuff because that would have hurt.
I've seen other people hurtling them and disappearing to the crowd almost.
I'm getting the ball back.
Quantarena.
For Italy.
Good deep serve.
Oh, yes.
In the groove straight away, they've had the change of ends, but three, two.
Wallet's back on it.
Wallet opens up the cross-court angle, and it doesn't matter what beer are any dents,
because Wallet is straight over the top of it.
And that tells you something, because he's two metres seven, bit of Ellie.
Well, these boys are hitting that ball about three, 53, 60,
but next two metres, 43, eight foot, same height as the cross-bar and foot built.
And these boys are getting way, way above it.
Quantare doing the same.
For straighting Lucas, as he goes past him.
Average height of both these teams.
One mid-97, six foot six.
Take that.
Absolutely unstoppable.
Just there side of the net, he may smile, but there's a grimace surely from Blengini and the rest.
Wonderful set again.
It's just opened up enough of an angle, but he keeps his left arm up.
He keeps his shoulder up to be able to hit over that shoulder and down into the angle.
If he'd have tried to turn with that, he'd have gone straight in the net.
There's a rhythm and there's assurance about Brazil at the moment.
And it's looking on him, it's ominous for Italy.
That may have gone into the net.
Yes, it's for all, but Italy now need to charge.
They need to kick on.
Because they've kept pace with Brazil and then at the crucial moments,
they've dropped behind and that's why Brazil lead this by two sets to love.
25-22, 28-26.
And when you're behind like that, those are becoming more and more costly.
We've had to come out somewhere.
Lanza, just off the touch.
Five all.
He's done a great job because, in the lens of Blengini,
took over last year and here he is.
The top table of volleyball in the gold medal match.
Back court pipe just too long from Leipa.
It's all about the speed.
They're getting the right timing between you and the setter.
But Italy read that very well and they put up some hands and that made it difficult
because there was a little room for Leipa to work with.
He's tried to change his mind and made the mistake.
Six all.
Hasn't been on song as he despite his name for Leipa Lanza.
It's one of those things for him.
He's kind of you look at the stars that are in the team and you look at a weak point
and you say well it's probably Lanza but actually he was an inspiration in their success
over the USA in the semi-final.
And for many people was the MVP.
Teraina gets the gap in the block again.
Good ball in and then as a defending team you're always going to be struggling.
Middle blocker Susa's never going to get out there in time and that's what you need.
Be able to have that gap to put the ball through because
Boutis doing his job to make the middle blocker wait and then have to go.
Isolated and then overloaded.
Seven six Italy.
Here's Wallace unloading and getting the points off the block.
Like a dog on a leash at the moment and Brazil just going hang on.
Whoops we'll just bring you back in again.
Seven all.
Not running away.
And it's relentless from Brazil.
Look at Ellie one small.
Look at Ellie's had some treatment on his back already.
And it was done out of the way behind the benches almost as if to say to Italy
that you haven't seen this because you just wonder if this does go on to third or fourth set.
Where the look is going to be actually managed to pace and that is an absolute baltap
from Susa that's going to hurt.
Serbian captain took it in the face and almost had a finger blown away
yesterday in the final against China was juteying the outstanding women player who took the
gold medal eventually but that was the mild matter Susa letting rip.
And here's trouble for Italy.
He's the Serbian king at the moment.
Anthony awaiting and now delivering but it's the wrong side of the net with that block.
Brazil take the point he didn't get through.
Again nice quick hit before the block can get set before they can close the hands towards the net.
Just thinking about that last sweep we just saw from Susa and what sprung to mind straight
away was the former middle blocker for Brazil Rodrig out who can hit that ball just like that day
in day out. We haven't seen it we've seen it first time from Susa but if he can do they just
could just meet. It gets any more like that it's going to be a real trouble for Italy.
Wallace standing start didn't finish a bit early at last
but the onslaught is just unrelenting that one pitballing around off Lucas and Bruno as
Wallace is stuffed.
Again level nine all third set best of five.
Good serve.
He is flyingly paid absolutely flying.
Yeah a little talking to from Resendys coach.
He just wants every ball right now he's a man who wants to with a plan he wants to make sure
that he gets a gold medal. He spent his life working towards this moment and he wants to make
sure that he takes it and if he doesn't he's given every single thing he possibly can to try and
achieve it. Don't need anything in the locker room. 10 9 Brazil at last for Biddo
Delhi and Giannelli. Quick fast set. That's what Blengini's wanting saying bravo bravo
because if they can't reestablish their middles again it becomes a really interesting battle
between the two teams.
Captain to serve.
That looks it was heading over the net but he was ready for it just waiting and anything
Italy can do Brazil can respond. And you will do if you run a middle against you you're going to
run a middle back against the other team you want to keep that pressure on both sides because
you're thinking the more this goes on the more that likely the middle is not going to be used
and you start edging out but then you can't you have to stay and so then you're ready and waiting
for those balls out wide as a hitzer knowing you've got one on one and it worked.
The
pay to serve. Italy have been warned.
Well actually digs. Back court pipe and that comes off quite a
ready and waiting and delivers. You're absolutely right it's not a pass at this level with
those guys hitting that jump serve it is a dig. You're defending that ball into an area where it
can be set. Sergio can't believe that didn't come back up. You'll throw himself at everything.
Zite's have tries for a special. The only people cheering are the Brazilian supporters.
Well just start to get a little bit tensed now for Italy. The more that their serves don't make it
in. The more Brazil are able to sideline the more Brazil are able to keep hold of this lead.
That's a top serve as well free ball here. Oh yes and guess who's done it.
To choose one small. It's too extreme we saw one where he's almost broke the ball and this
one where he goes that realizes I can't hit this I've got the blocker in front of me but it's
lands there in front of me tip over him no one able to cover.
Until eight days ago Italy had never beaten Brazil in the Olympics played eight lost eight
but they scored a notable win in the pool matches but now when it really counts this is the
gold medal match it he have never won the gold medal Brazil are asserting themselves once more
here's Lucas what a serve somehow it's still in play though brilliant dig
was he missed he has as the first mistake by Dessousa in almost two and a half sets play to the whistle
you don't play to what you think you've seen that was a cracking serve no data about it it's pin
balled around the Italian passing unit but everyone's linked in and then it's dug back over
whilst Brazil was celebrating now the question is has that caught the hair of booties it goes past him
if it has it's a touch the only time it doesn't come is if your hair touches the net and then it's
not a touch but that ball hasn't touched anything or anyone except the outside of the court and so
Italy have the point
oh yes
genelium beauty you beauty 13 all that got a little bit tight over towards the left hand side
of court it was favoring where the Italians were moving and so the double combination over
the top of Susid gave Luke Carelli no room at all
that's frustrating they're creeping in more and more now aren't they but it's the fact that it's
it's a jump float serve as well you can understand it if it's a jump serve with the way that these
guys hit in the ball and there'll be no worries from the team but when the jump float serve doesn't
go in that can spark a little bit of it from the rest of the guys
absolutely the perfect way to make up for it lands and knows he made an error with his serve
but he's come right back he's put the ball on a plate for genelie he's able to find
zite's head they're back in the game and his missed serve earlier is completely forgotten
brilliant work from the slow mo you can see how high suits it gets
still stuck together in his third set beauty
Wallace and then off the block they take the point one thing that brazil are doing far better
than it's at the moment is their ability to deal with that five to five serve because brazil
using it it's near using it but leap eight is passing that ball in brilliantly and brazil
are siding out without any issues change up here for brazil marizio has coming in marizio has
been the starting outside hitter for brazil in this tournament but has lost his place to leap
eight lucarelli we know is suffering a little bit with injury and he's probably going to get
set scene two potentially by the physio but certainly we'll be reigning to come back in but just
being given a rest at the moment in the back row wanted for front court duties marizio is going
to come in and serve the five position just to remind you is in the bottom left of the back court
on both sides off the block brazil 15 all their keeping pace
the longer this third set goes on the more you can just feel the tension rise on that blue side
of the net because they know they have to win this set to stand the match
best of five without this reaching over surely by Bruno and it was a legal touch there pulling it
back from the Italian side of the net it's leap just get ahead and get the serve
not so fast let's have a time out
brazilian team have been in the Olympics before Bruno
Wallace the number four Sergio the libero and Lucas that big middle blocker the rest though
this is their first Olympics and what a venue their home court in front of their home crowd
and they're leading two sets to love
another mighty block
17 15
sites have developing a bit of a momentum
he was ready just hanging there wasn't he
a very good work from sites have lining up leapay
and making sure he didn't get the ball over
it's over that's a bigger achievement from Gneli
and that's through and long no touch 18 15 well there's issues here for
wands arenas that ball has been ripped off his fingers with the the call is gone against
brazil for Wallace coming through and hitting the net it might actually have been Wallace's
hand that smashed onto wands arenas
oh it is so Wallace actually is come through and he's dragged
wands arenas hand down onto the net
wands arenas the person who's touched the net here i'm interested to see if there's
going to be a challenge whether that will go against wands arenas but in fact what's happened is
he's been pulled onto the net by Wallace
and Italy have the point much to the frustration of Bruno
De Zendé the coach Bernardo De Zendé
and Pontorayna having words as well oh
challenge that there's a really reversed that then
woman he was giving it now he's just reversed it
so Peter really quite rightly saying that's it
Wallace pulled wands arenas down onto the net
but the bottom line is when terrain attached the net
well two decisions for the price of one that
and the one which sticks famous brazil
oh a set went completely wrong
trying to make a negative set into the middle
so that meant Jean-Ele having to hold the ball and then fire it back out
and he didn't send it out quickly enough
how much of a momentum switch is this
yes it's only 17 or but Italy seems to be moving clear
and it's a charm
style they have to clear the mind again and go once more
because brazil know if they take this set it's all over
they have a gold medal
he's got it through
that's a quality hit from Zaitsepp triple block
and he finds a gap the nearest gap between Wallace and
Lucas and exploits it
sometimes you go for power otherwise that could be a tip over
but it's an element of frustration really that's building
among the Italian team they're yet really to hit top form
Brazil just haven't let them
and that's in
they're on it 18 all they have top form
and they're pretty much in top gear
huge rotations from Wallace from right to left
as he hits the ball when he lands he's pretty much
almost got his back side to the net at times
such as his rotation which is why he's so good at hitting
through the right hand side of court but not so good
over on the left hand side
that's going to be a double touch against Giannelli
this is running away from Blanjini and Italy
whatever their feelings about that challenge which Brazil
seemingly lost then one
they have to regroup and that's what they are doing
time out
well that's it for Blanjini no more timeouts
the players may get the chance to talk to him again if Brazil
go for a time out they're not quite on their own
because he can still offer instructions but the crowd believing
that the momentum the force is with Brazil and they're
going to be celebrating shortly at Olympic gold medal
for the home nation
and he's six more points
not so fast 19 all
but it's you're not quite up to game speed as Lanza crashes that one
through the block and it'll make to react great swing from Philip
Elanza
Wallace arrives and unloads inside the court
they're up to 20
oh Wallace gives this absolute spanking
but it's all the intent Wallace and Lepe and Suza
they are they mean business from start to finish you they have come out with
a plan and they are delivering
here is Lepe just out he's being spurred on the fans screaming his name as he
lined up to serve that one maybe just a extra adrenaline surges he
hit through the ball
Italy pretty much hanging on the team which set the tournament alive in the
opening match thrashing the European champions three love
they were eight love to the good in the first set
fantastic performance
and when Zite's serve doesn't fire properly Italy have problems
Well Blangini had said to the guys in the timeout
let's we need to risk this we need to be brave on serve and we need to be brave
and receive and they need to get their middle running but at the moment
it's Brazil who are making all the running
nice arrival from Quantorena yes the hand hurt from Wallace a few moments ago
but take that take it out on the ball
brilliant timing they were trying to get towards Wantorena but they had to watch
what Bouti was doing and that meant they couldn't commit fully
and Wantorena makes the best use of the ball Rossini is in
full-anzer serving passing defending from him
oh bro no they're captain first one of the match and he makes it look as if it's
the most natural thing in the world if they were waiting for the set take that
lack of discipline from Italy but late on in the match that's something that
you can expect to happen you've got a set a front row you've got a key in on
the set as touch then the quick attack then the second
tempo then the ball wide they didn't do their first job
that's long or what the retouch name I think it wasn't a touch
Italy thinks it was a touch we're going to have a challenge and we're going to
find out whether there was a touch because if there was it's 22 or if there
wasn't massive touch so we're going to get his
finger back from the ball
so the challenge will be successful and it will be 22 or
and it's still very much game on and Italy is still very much in this
who's going to blink in the last two sets Brazil
just hell firm and Italy subsided now what a moment for
Oleg Antonov his first Olympic games this needs to be an absolute wowser
first and foremost he's got to make Brazil play this ball
he has but the problem is Wallace is coming for him
and Wallace has done what he wanted
23 22 two more points they will be Olympic champions for the third time
Wallace swing that is from Wallace underlying his commitment to the cause
and his desire to win this match and get a gold medal
where Gini trying to be heard it is a cacophony of sound here
Brazil closing in Italy desperate to get this back
he'll actually digs you're an Ellie it's only a tip from side serve now they came
there was a touch referee agrees 23 all
well he's just wonder whether Blaine Gini was feeling a little bit no
side off that Gini feeling a little bit nervous he's been told run the middle run the middle
Bira Ellie was there wanting the ball he's got all we're going to go behind
does I said that it wasn't a great set but it came off does I said a saved his blushes that's for sure
Gini to serve
what a jump and Wallace off the block has match point for Brazil
they've been here before four years ago they had match point twice couldn't take it twice
they know they need to do this now because of Italy side out it's a two point game again
and that means signing out for the set or signing out for the match
their fourth consecutive final gold in 2004 two successive silvers is it going to be gold in
2016 site toe goes for the tip and they've saved match point 24 all calmness
under pressure from site set gets the roll shot off the block and away
and now it's a two point set Italy need two points clear to take the set
Brazil need two points to win a gold medal lands us back in into the front row
Rossini's gone to the bench went to Reyna with the serve
it's a good one but Brazil still having him play and they're off the block Lucas
the veteran from 2012 has teed up their second match point
Brazil are going to have to do it the hard way though they are going to have to do it
from service we're back to old school volleyball if they want to win this one
they've got to be tough from the serve their block defense has to work they've got to get into
transition and attack any one of those three will do
blocking substitution if androas come in Bruno has gone off no recognized setter on court
here for Brazil they're just going to try and shut down Italy at the net
gold medal points for the hosts and doesn't the home crowd know it
Wallace
off the block it's all over Brazil are Olympic champions
for the fourth time they've been in the final they won in 2004 they let it slip in 2008
and 2012 but in 2016 on their home court in Rio de Janeiro
Brazil are the Olympic champions again for the third time
or there's an EO there's a challenge the drama is ratcheted up once more it's a little challenging
to be fair he's got no other option well plan genies maybe just the last throw the dice
and that's it they have a challenge it's been denied they waited too long that surely was beyond
the five second mark and Sergio has won his fourth Olympic medal it's his second gold medal he
retired after 2012 but he was brought back last year in the world league and here he is an Olympic
champion again and the Maracazinho in the shadow of the Maracaná were Neymar who's there watching
and won the gold medal with the football team 24 hours before they have witnessed another
Brazilian triumph in the world of volleyball they have been the supreme force throughout the
2000s three time the world champions and they've overcome Italy for the second time in the final
there is Neymar he was in tears yesterday but he did the job and so to have his countryman
in the yellow and blue their famous colors on the court at the Maracaná Zinho Italy cannot believe it
three sets to love they're only lost once before in this tournament but at the most significant time
they have gone down and Neymar and Bruno resend his third Olympics the captain of the team
and it's a volleyball double Alice on and Bruno took the beach volleyball and now the men's team
have risen and they will be on the top step of the podium accepting bronze medals and it's a
mighty achievement to only two other countries have one gold on their home court the USSR 1980
and the USA in LA in 1984
the USA have been introduced and they will step up to receive their bronze medals
at one stage seemingly heading out of the competition after two big defeats early on but they battle
back and they take their medals on the third step of the podium but what a performance it was
from Matt Anderson this team who lost out in the semi-final in one of the matches the greatest
of matches we've probably seen for a long time and maybe for a long time to come when they went
out in five sets to Italy but bounce back and beat Russia in five sets again so I had to pick
themselves up dust themselves down and come back and battle it out with what were the defending
Olympic champions up to that point and they did it magnificently Matt Anderson it was you hit the
winner in the end who took the medal first the captain and for that man William Pretty as well
came coming on as a substitute to turn the course of that match in the favor of the USA after
Aaron Russell who had been a superstar for the tournament just couldn't quite get his game going
but to have that strength in depth which is what's required even though Murphy Troy didn't play in
that in that bronze medal match very much an influential player within the course of the proceedings
Jeski came on court as well and did his bit and Mika Christensen in the back to receive his medal
was outstanding just leading the way setting the balls up allowing Maxwell Holt to have an absolute
blinder going through the middle he was superb David Smith another middle blocker who again
come on and did his part when required during the course of the tournament and for Eric Shoji
the libera back to get his medal a special moment for him because he made some outstanding digs
some great defensive plays superb with his passing they can all be proud of what they've achieved
they came back after that defeat to take that bronze medal and they will be enjoying this moment
what a moment for William Pretty there just on the left of your picture 38 years old
he's a veteran of so many USA volleyball campaigns
and he has another medal to put around his neck
they've emulated the women's team who also were knocked out in the semi-finals but came back to take
the bronze medal and they were willing them on during the course of this bronze medal
actually entire women's team were sat watching cheering them on and they will all go home to the USA
as heroes and heroines pretty and David Lee both won gold in 2008 when the team to their right
were their opponents in the final in Beijing and America came out on top
but for these players coming down the line Maxwell Holt at his first big medal and
sure it'll just wet the appetite to come back for more in Japan in four years time
the bronze medalists in the men's volleyball just like their women counterparts they are still a force
Italy
bronze medalists in 2012
they've gone one better but how they wanted it to be the ultimate prize the gold medal which
still eludes them their third silver in Olympic competition to 1996 and 2004 ad 2016
so today he came on he's the backup set up for it he had a good serving run and gave them opportunities
it's one of those where this is mixed emotions for Italy the fact that he didn't quite see things
over the line and yet they are here getting themselves a silver medal. Wantarena was beside
himself with tears at the end of the match knowing that they were beaten they can have no complaints
when they look back because at the end of the day it was a consummate performance from the
Brazilian team Ginelli just taking his medal it was Satila Luka Vettore who took the other opposite
player who picked up his as well as we go along the line and Rossini who's normally a Libro for
the Italian team being brought in as a passer-hitter the Zah Zah Zah Zah so much was relying on him and
look at that he's even gone off and he's had a shave and spruced himself up ready for this medal
ceremony. Lanza was very good probably the most valuable player in their win to not the USA acts
in the semi-finals. Pute again was brilliant everything he got through the middle he put away
Colachi well I think he was probably one of the best liberos we've seen in the tournament it's so
hard to decide between them when you look at him and you look at Shoji and you look at Sergio the
three best Libros have got medals around their necks and rightly so for Piano well he had his
chances didn't take the most of them and was a bystander for the this gold medal match in
Bira Rely what a performance from him the captain of Italy and for Antonov as well came in and did
his bit but in the end it just wasn't quite to be but when they look back on this what a pride
moment for that bronze in 2012 and now a silver here in Rio 2016 the only game they lost three sets
to love was in the final against Brazil they went down with a weakened team against Canada in the
final match of Pulae but they were already guaranteed a place in the quarter finals and you
wonder how many of these this team will be back in Japan. So till a 37 1 3 in a 31 certainly that
man will Simone Giannelli 20 years old Zaitsev just 27 top scorer for Italy in the not just the
tournament but over in this match to just other 17 points. Lanza Felipe Lanza 25 Bouti 32
Rossini also in his 30s Piano will come again the tallest man 6 foot 10 2 meters 8 Bira Rely 35
years old but he has a medal another one to show for his magnificent efforts and leadership
they're getting closer
the world number one team are the Olympic champions for 2016 and it couldn't be sweeter
on their home court in front of their home crowd in Rio de Janeiro
well it's a stunning performance the captain Bruno picking up his medal some inspired setting choices
from him some super blocking as well and and serving to back it up for Adé Bigred he was a very
influential member of this team and that means so much to him as you can tell Wallace what a performance
a man full of desire and belief and determination in that final that he was not going to be walking
away with a silver medal 20 points for him during the course of that final his Santa Cruzero teammate
William who came in in the double substitution he's just struggling with the weight of that gold
medal to stand out that's brilliant and for Luccarelli well the tears for Luccarelli
and particularly for that man Sergio 40 years of age retired was brought back and he's now
going to retire again with a gold medal round his neck he thought he was all over in London when
he got the silver but now look what he has and leapay for me I think the man of the match he was
a substitute at the start of this tournament but he got his chance on court ahead of Mauricio he
took it and he led this team in the final along with Wallace Suza was brilliant had an injury at the
start of this tournament and wasn't playing and then got fit for Douglas what an experience for
this young man the future of Brazilian volleyball in the outside hitting position just 21 years of age
we expect to see a lot more of him Lucas again was brilliant teaming up with Bruno hitting some
superb quick attacks if Andrew came on and did his job as the backup opposite player when
Brazil ran their double substitutions to put him into the front row and Luccarelli that young man
can be so proud having to battle through injury in the final not just with his tie but also a back
injury as well and it was he who let leapay really run the show liqueur really did his job Mauricio also
came in and did his job having lost his place on court to leapay but still very much a team effort
and it required everyone in order for them to have those gold medals around their next
how special for Sergio he started this run of four Olympic games with a gold medal in Athens
against the same opposition three one they won against Italy and now two bronzes two silver's
rather and now a gold medal what a way to bow out and he joins a very elite group of four time
medalists so a guy Tetshikin of Russia and also some well he pappy of Italy it's almost as if
this means more than the first some might say is it really unexpected why should it mean that much
they are the world number one team they may have lost the world league to Serbia's men in the final
in Japan but this was their home court there was so much to expect when he was the one who said after
the first said of their loss to the against mexico it's those rings once your own court you suddenly
realize where you are and it was real and so much was expected and they dealt with that pressure brilliantly
they could have crumbled they could have gone out the psychological battles in this sport are huge
but that ability and I think if anything this 12 000 strong american azineo cry just carried
them along when they needed it and lifted them to new levels of sport and the same two can be
said for italy in the USA in some of the most memorable volleyball we've seen
as with the national anthem sung so lustily in the madakana to mark the brazil football team winning
the goal medal so another rousing rendition of brazil's national anthem too much for Sergio and the
captain Brazil the goal medallists in their home country italy silver medallists again and the USA
coming good and taking the bronze medal moments they will treasure particularly the Brazilian players
for a lifetime to inspire them to go forward for further success and for italy this should act
too as a catalyst knowing that they are back right at the forefront of the game can america come good too
Japan 2020 is still four years off but the rebuilding the regrouping and the planning will start now
well that's a huge gesture towards murillo who couldn't make these games because he was injured and he had
to bow out and what a gesture that is from the team in recognition of all his efforts in helping them
to get to these Olympic games and be prepared in the way they were and ultimately be able to take the
gold medal he was shattered not to be involved murillo the captain from 2012
part of the journey from 2004 2008 2012 but just in the last few months the injuries got
the better of him age 35 he couldn't be part of the team
then genie it is first year as Italian coach Olympic silver medalist
it's all smiles for the hosts what a part is in store in reo
they are on top of the world again in men's volleyball
just shows you what a team effort is and how many people are involved not just the players on court in making it happen
it didn't happen for the women's indoor volleyball team and there were tears then
six days ago when they were beaten by china but it's all come good now for brosils men how many pictures
how many autographs how many victory celebrations they will be the toast of re addition hero along
with the football team and the beach volleyball players Alissa on and Bruno how long will they stay inside
the Maracas in you to be worshiped and faded by this capacity crowd
this could be a team dive is certainly going to be a pretty special celebration led by Sergio four times
only brosil and only in reo but when you are Olympic champions for the third time in your home country
there is no limit to the celebrations